<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://kennethrioja.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://kennethrioja.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2024-03-15T12:54:18+00:00</updated><id>https://kennethrioja.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>Research, EdTech, Video Games, Data Analysis, UX </subtitle><entry><title type="html">Using mutate with multiple conditions including grepl in R</title><link href="https://kennethrioja.github.io/blog/2024/using-mutate-with-multiple-conditions-including-grepl-in-r/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Using mutate with multiple conditions including grepl in R"/><published>2024-03-14T13:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-03-14T13:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://kennethrioja.github.io/blog/2024/using-mutate-with-multiple-conditions-including-grepl-in-r</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://kennethrioja.github.io/blog/2024/using-mutate-with-multiple-conditions-including-grepl-in-r/"><![CDATA[<p>In my case, I had one <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">id</code> containing two games/sessions, as shown by different dates in my column <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">timeStamp</code> which is of <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">char</code> data type in the raw data.</p> <p>The example below shows how I differenciated the two IDs. Let’s say the second player played the game on March 14, 2024 and I want to change it’s <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">id</code> to <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">"2"</code>.</p> <div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>df &lt;- raw %&gt;%
  dplyr::mutate(id = ifelse((grepl("^20240314.*$", timeStamp, ignore.case = TRUE) # if timeStamp begins by "20240314"
                              &amp; id == "1"), # and id is "1"
                              "2", # change id to "2"
                              id)) # else keep it as is
</code></pre></div></div> <hr/> <p>Regex tips:</p> <p><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">^</code> marks the begining of the string, <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">.*</code> marks anything (like the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">*</code> in C), <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">$</code> marks the end of the string</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="R"/><category term="data"/><category term="code"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Damn it Regex]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Screen consumption recommendations during early childhood</title><link href="https://kennethrioja.github.io/blog/2024/screen-consumption-recommendations-during-early-childhood/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Screen consumption recommendations during early childhood"/><published>2024-02-27T20:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-02-27T20:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://kennethrioja.github.io/blog/2024/screen-consumption-recommendations-during-early-childhood</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://kennethrioja.github.io/blog/2024/screen-consumption-recommendations-during-early-childhood/"><![CDATA[<p>I am getting surrounded by more and more young parents and if I were to provide them with scientific-based recommendations in two minutes, I would redirect them to <a href="https://www.unige.ch/fapse/sensori-moteur/membres/eg">Edouard Gentaz</a>’ recommendations:</p> <ol> <li>Limit screen consumption as best as you can before two years old.</li> <li>No screen during meals (to limit or avoid <a href="https://www.academia.edu/15735501/_Technoference_Everyday_Intrusions_and_Interruptions_of_Technology_in_Couple_and_Family_Relationships">technoference</a>, also applicable to your couple life!)</li> <li>No screen during waking-up in the morning.</li> <li>Avoid alone and passive consumption for the child.</li> <li>Control the quality of what’s been consumed.</li> </ol> <p>Edouard Gentaz is a professor at the faculty of Psychology of the University of Geneva. The above points come from a public seminar I highly enjoyed and I encourage you to <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=kXtX3C9SchE">watch the whole talk on YouTube</a>!</p> <p>If you are interested in the topic of screens and children / adolescents, the <a href="https://www.unige.ch/centre-piaget/activites-scientifiques/seminaire-piaget/2024">Centre Jean Piaget</a> (<a href="https://www.unige.ch/fapse/">FPSE, University of Geneva</a>) is currently offering public seminars, every Wednesday at 18:15 in room M1170 at <a href="https://www.google.fr/maps/place/Uni+Mail,+Bd+du+Pont-d'Arve+40,+1205+Gen%C3%A8ve/@46.1949191,6.1372961,17z/data=!3m1!4b1!4m6!3m5!1s0x478c7ad59a95c06f:0x405b734617bdd72c!8m2!3d46.1949154!4d6.139871!16s%2Fg%2F1tdyppds?entry=ttu">Unimail</a>.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="university"/><category term="research"/><category term="psychology"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Are you pro or anti screen?]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">What would be the learning space of your dreams?</title><link href="https://kennethrioja.github.io/blog/2024/eduspace-challenge/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What would be the learning space of your dreams?"/><published>2024-02-06T14:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-02-06T14:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://kennethrioja.github.io/blog/2024/eduspace-challenge</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://kennethrioja.github.io/blog/2024/eduspace-challenge/"><![CDATA[<div class="row"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/blog_edsc2024-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/blog_edsc2024-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/blog_edsc2024-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/blog_edsc2024.jpeg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" title="eduspace challenge team 2024" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Finding Kenneth 🔍 </div> <p>All started by a post in the internal forum of the Master <a href="https://maltt.unige.ch/">MALTT</a>. Students from all over Switzerland were invited to take part of a hackathon during the <a href="https://eduhubdays2024.events.switch.ch/">EduHub Days</a> in Winterthur. The pitch: two days in <a href="https://www.zhaw.ch/fr/universite/">ZHAW</a>, use Design Thinking to ideate on future learning spaces.</p> <p>After applicating to the call, I got selected to be part of this adventure! Thank you <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/lisa-messenzehl-5b777b19a/">Lisa</a>, <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/tereza-karag%C3%BClle-405503b2/">Tereza</a> and <a href="https://www.switch.ch/">Switch</a> for the opportunity!</p> <p>First day, on February 7, we attended a key note by <a href="https://www.james858499.net/">James Lamb</a> about post digital learning spaces of higher education (<a href="https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/s42438-021-00279-9">Lamb et al., 2021</a>). A learning space is any setting where learning and teaching activities take place. Also a learning space is heavily contingent on the context, so this is why he gave us not tips, but ways on how to build the best learning space. He made a list of six points :</p> <ol> <li><em>An online space is always also a physical space</em>. As he mentionned <a href="https://doi.org/10.1007/s42438-021-00265-1">Gourlay (2021)</a>, there are no ‘virtual learning’, the learning is always a true experience.</li> <li><em>Create space for imagination</em>. He emphasized that digital technology must be seen as a ressource (active in the process) and not as a passive tool.</li> <li><em>Innovation without exclusion</em>. “All students like this”, well… maybe not! James mentionned that we should be able to achieve through mixed reality what cannot be achieved in physical or online (<a href="https://doi.org/10.1080/14626268.2018.1511601">Flint et al., 2018</a>).</li> <li><em>Attend to the aesthetics, emotional &amp; sensory elements of a learning space</em>. This point resonated in me. Aesthetics matter indeed, but we are often not taught much about the importance of aesthetics. “It is of first importance to make a learning space work in a mechanical way, the aesthetics come after”, this is what I often hear unfortunately. Only few passionate students are able to create something at the same level of design and aesthetic than most of the new tech companies.</li> <li><em>Pursue pleasure and make room for play</em>. There should be a link between formal and informal learning spaces (<a href="https://brill.com/downloadpdf/book/9789460916090/BP000005.pdf">Boys, 2011</a>) and the environment should be pleasant (e.g., plants, color, light, music).</li> <li><em>Every learning space should be assigned in harmony with our natural world</em>. We must “reimagine sustainable forms of education technology” (<a href="https://www.academia.edu/download/98619725/Unesco_Background_Ed_Tech.pdf">Facer &amp; Selwyn, 2021</a>)</li> </ol> <p>Then came one full day of Design Thinking. I teamed up with <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/davide-ghielmetti-033732a5/">Davide</a> from economics, <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/isabella-loder-21419b21b/">Isabella</a> from health promotion and prevention and Sara from education. It was a rich experience to work with students from different backgrounds, which is not an opportunity often given at the university! Also I found challenging to create and pitch our idea in less than eight hours of work. I applause the time management from our coach <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/martinarechsteiner/">Martina</a>!</p> <p>Moreover, when talking with peers of my Master curriculum, we felt like we have not learned anything new in terms of digital technologies from this design thinking workshop. I personnally think that most of the limitations and implications of what it is to have the ideal learning setup (online, physical, synchronous, asynchronous, etc.) was already taught and discussed in class (see <a href="https://edutechwiki.unige.ch/fr/ADID">ADID EduTechWiki page</a> for more information).</p> <p>From all the ideas of what could be a future learning space, words like “personalisation”, “students’ needs”, “goal” were repeatedly used.</p> <p>Link to the promotional video of the event: https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=dWy5iNByxQ4</p> <p>Link to another blog post (en français) in the CIEL blog of the UNIGE where I share my experience:</p> <hr/> <p>What I will keep in mind after these two days :</p> <ol> <li>Aesthetics matter in digital technologies. I would advise schools to give proper credit compared to coding. When “designing” digital technologies, instructional designers should give 50% of their time to the mechanistic part of learning, and 50% of their time to making it enjoyable and appealing.</li> <li>Personalisation is one of the most important students’ need for digital technologies.</li> </ol>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="research"/><category term="edtech"/><category term="ui"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Using design thinking to build the future learning space at EduSpace Challenge]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">How to convert cm to px in a screen?</title><link href="https://kennethrioja.github.io/blog/2024/convert-cm-in-px/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How to convert cm to px in a screen?"/><published>2024-02-04T12:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-02-04T12:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://kennethrioja.github.io/blog/2024/convert-cm-in-px</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://kennethrioja.github.io/blog/2024/convert-cm-in-px/"><![CDATA[<p>Never report <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">px</code> in a research paper when you want to communicate about a stimulus size on screen, it is not a sign of reproducibility because the pixel size of my screen is not necessarily the same pixel size than yours.</p> <blockquote> <p><a href="http://i.stack.imgur.com/cDCvQ.jpg">All three of these</a> have 1920x1080 px screens. – <a href="https://superuser.com/users/194694/gronostaj">gronostaj</a> in <a href="https://superuser.com/questions/1103934/does-1-pixel-have-a-standard-size">this forum</a></p> </blockquote> <p>The variables / constants you must have are :</p> <ul> <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">distanceFromScreen</code> usually 50 cm (<a href="https://www.jove.com/t/52470/methods-to-test-visual-attention-online">Yung et al., 2015</a>)</li> <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">pxPerDeg</code> (to compute it, you can use <a href="https://res18h39.netlify.app/calculator">this calculator</a>)</li> <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">expectedStimulusSizeWidth</code></li> </ul> <p>Here is the JS code to compute the expected size (in cm) of a stimuli :</p> <div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>const   stimWidthRad = 2 * Math.atan((expectedStimulusSizeWidth / 2) / distanceFromScreen); // stimulus width in radian
const   stimWidthDeg = stimWidthRad * 180 / Math.PI; // stimulus width in degrees
const   stimWidthPx = stimWidthDeg * pxPerDeg; // stim width in px from real monitor size in cm.
</code></pre></div></div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="research"/><category term="code"/><category term="psychology"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[What you see is not what reality is]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">What is it to be in a free computer science school?</title><link href="https://kennethrioja.github.io/blog/2024/42-is-over/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What is it to be in a free computer science school?"/><published>2024-01-20T22:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-01-20T22:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://kennethrioja.github.io/blog/2024/42-is-over</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://kennethrioja.github.io/blog/2024/42-is-over/"><![CDATA[<div class="row"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> </div> <div class="col-sm-5 mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/blog_42isover-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/blog_42isover-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/blog_42isover-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/blog_42isover.jpeg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" title="sunset from train holding 1984" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Coming back to Geneva, with a beautiful sunset and the agreable feeling of completing the common core of <a href="https://42lausanne.ch/">42 Lausanne</a>. </div> <p><em>“Common core: The curriculum at <a href="https://42lausanne.ch/">42</a> starts with the core curriculum. This experience sets the base for minimum skills, both human and technical. (…) [it] lets students learn C programming, develop simple software using classic algorithms, discover access to the file system, and learn management of the UNIX process. It also includes a simple first approach to network architecture as well as system administration. The program also offers oriented programming and a client-server project”</em> – <a href="https://42.fr/en/the-program/software-engineer-degree/">42</a></p> <p>A computer school with no courses, no hours, no teachers and tuition-free. That was the promise made and kept by <a href="https://42lausanne.ch/">42 Lausanne</a>! The beginning of my coding journey started when I began using <a href="https://www.r-project.org/">R</a> during my full-time research assistant position at the <a href="https://www.unige.ch/fapse/brainlearning/">Bavelierlab</a>. For me, it was sort of coding and I loved it. Being able to automatize through scripts was a timesaver for me! My lab director pushed me to look for computer science schools. Fortunately for me, 42 was opening a new campus in Lausanne! I gave it a shot and I was not disappointed.</p> <p>After two years and a half (August 2021 – January 2024) at 42, I am now taking a step back and this is what I see :</p> <p><em>Step 1: The ‘Piscine’.</em> I spent the best one month of peer-learning how to code in C.</p> <p><em>Step 2: Finding the right balance.</em> During the first year, it was a real challenge to make 42 Lausanne, my <a href="https://maltt.unige.ch/master/qui-sommes-nous/">Master</a> and the part-time job at the lab work together. I successfully handled it and the first year was a total bliss. How satisfying it was to get the work done and to know more and more computer science concepts!</p> <p><em>Step 3: Loneliness.</em> At the beginning of the second year, it began harder to find people progressing at the same pace. I began to work almost on my own and let me tell you this is not how the school experience (and learning in general) should be. <a href="https://doi.org/10.3102/00346543071003449">You always learn best when confronting your ideas to other people (Lou et al., 2001)</a>.</p> <p><em>Step 4: Disillusion.</em> Towards the end of the second year, I was always finishing my projects at less than five days of being kicked out the school. I remember hard moments at the edge of the Black Hole (name given to the day-counter of the school). Completing the 42 curriculum, for what? I will be forever thankful to my girlfriend who relentlessly supported me, making me stop my endless questionning of the purpose of completing 42.</p> <p><em>Step 5: Freedom.</em> On the 22nd of December, I finished the last project of the common core <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">transcendence</code> and on the 20th of January I passed my last exam. Finally !!! 🎉 The last comment made at the last evaluation for the project was: <em>“Mention: Dégage de mon common core”</em>, sure I will!</p> <p>A note for the educational researchers out there! I find clever the whole 42 organization : “come as you are”, no discrimination, no prerequisites, no hierarchical pressure, only you come and learn because you want it. <em>Autonomy</em>. Then nudging the people to meet new colleagues by enforcing peer-evaluation and group work. The more you evaluate, the more you know people, the more you connect with the people you enjoy being with. <em>Relatedness</em>. Engaging the people in the whole process, making them acquiring new skills, then introduce them to the people who fund the institution. <em>Competence</em>. Yes, this is how you create self-determination in students (<a href="https://selfdeterminationtheory.org/SDT/documents/2000_RyanDeci_SDT.pdf">Deci &amp; Ryan, 1985</a>)</p> <hr/> <p>For you, the IT or code newbie, it is up to you to engage in such a process but here are my arguments on why you should join 42 Lausanne:</p> <ol> <li>I met like-minded people who are now close friends (SO <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/victor-vermot-petit-outhenin-02786b23b/">Victor</a>, <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/romainhoarau/">Romain</a> and <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/joseph-e/">Yossi</a>). And to say the truth, I was not expecting this AT ALL nor tried to make new friends at the begining!</li> <li>Acquiring these global tech knowledge and skills opened me to new opportunities. I began following my dream, developping video games and sharing this dream with people I met in 42. I was given other tasks at the lab, interpreting researchers needs for a web developper to build an experiment management system. And finally I felt confident in accepting an internship at the <a href="https://www.lip-unige.ch/2024/01/23/en-avant-vers-2024/">LIP</a> which consists in developping a REST API to collect logs from an educational video game made with Unity.</li> <li>New opportunities can never finish with the multiple events made at 42 Lausanne, most of the time inviting start-ups, partners and tech companies!</li> <li>Be courageous and be sure to count on your loved ones if you are currently engaged in multiple activities / jobs / hobbies.</li> </ol>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="work"/><category term="code"/><category term="misc"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[My learnings after two years at 42 Lausanne]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">What comes to mind if you read “Start-up”?</title><link href="https://kennethrioja.github.io/blog/2023/innosuisse-business-training-concept/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What comes to mind if you read “Start-up”?"/><published>2023-12-11T12:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-12-11T12:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://kennethrioja.github.io/blog/2023/innosuisse-business-training-concept</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://kennethrioja.github.io/blog/2023/innosuisse-business-training-concept/"><![CDATA[<div class="row"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/blog_ibct2023-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/blog_ibct2023-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/blog_ibct2023-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/blog_ibct2023.jpeg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" title="a class group" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Finding Kenneth 🔍 </div> <p>I was introduced to this EPFL course through the <a href="https://www.unige.ch/unitec/fr/actualite/conference/">Unitec, “Valorisation de la recherche” course</a>. Coming from psychology, educational technologies, and working as a lab assistant during four years, the option of pursuing an academic career was THE option. However, I wanted to create more than to do fundamental research. What were the options offered after finishing a <a href="https://maltt.unige.ch">Master in Learning and Teaching Technologies</a>? What about creating a start-up that would go beyond the limitations often taught in the field? A lot of good ideas were stemming from the fruitful discussions between students, assistants and teachers but most of them, unfortunately, are now remaining in limbo or are totally forgotten. I think it’s a shame.</p> <p>I also think that students, at their early stages in the University, should be introduced to what it is to create a start-up. At least, they should be introduced to knowing the actors and the economic processes underlying a <em>capitalist</em> world. One observation I have made is that 90% of the people attending the start-up events at the university of Geneva are PhD students or Post-Docs.</p> <p>When I began the first courses in September 2023, it was very disturbing for me. I felt like I was not in the right place. When you are willing to create your own start-up, for sure you must be confident and believe in yourself otherwise people might not trust your ideas and vision. Then, I found out that most of this was a facade and the people were, like me, attending the practical course to learn.</p> <p>Being impressed by this new environment, I did not suggest any start-up idea (and this was a shame too ha!). Despite my lack of idea, I joined the development of Rebuild.easy. This start-up aims at providing an online platform helping house owners who want to renovate their real estate by offering them a one-stop-shop and no upfront cost. I teamed up with two great people : <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/jean-ventura-6bba8150/">Jean Ventura</a> the founder and <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/steven-schramiak-2005/">Steven Schramiak</a> the business mastermind. The project attracted me first because of the energy and friendly aura from Jean, and second because house renovation was my week-end activity during the last two years.</p> <hr/> <p>Here is what I learned during the entire semester (<a href="https://github.com/kennethrioja/secondbrain/blob/main/talks.md#11122023--unige-innosuisse-business-training-concept">here</a> for more tips):</p> <ol> <li> <p>I discovered the small Swiss startup ecosystem and few of their actors (for example, <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/company/fongit/">FONGIT</a>, <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/company/venturelab/">VentureLab</a>, <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/company/genilem/">GENILEM</a>, <a href="https://www.unige.ch/unitec/fr/">Unitec</a>). I now know the network if someday I want to create my own start-up.</p> </li> <li> <p>I got introduced to finance, law and economics. “Cash is king”, they say.</p> </li> <li> <p>Market research is the core pilar of your start-up – like UX for a product. Find the needs!</p> </li> </ol> <p>When I now hear start-up, I see either people passionate about their work and trying to solve a current problem, either people who are grabbing opportunities that the current world is offering. What about you?</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="work"/><category term="research"/><category term="edtech"/><category term="misc"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[One semester attending Innosuisse Business Training Concept course]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">How to be a better leader?</title><link href="https://kennethrioja.github.io/blog/2023/be-a-better-leader/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How to be a better leader?"/><published>2023-12-04T13:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-12-04T13:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://kennethrioja.github.io/blog/2023/be-a-better-leader</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://kennethrioja.github.io/blog/2023/be-a-better-leader/"><![CDATA[<div class="row"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> </div> <div class="col-sm-5 mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/blog_bookTDC-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/blog_bookTDC-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/blog_bookTDC-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/blog_bookTDC.jpeg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" title="book trillion dollar coach" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> First, read this book (or at least the following review). </div> <p>One month ago, <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/aviram/">Avi Ram</a> (an experienced International Business Program Director and Change Manager) was the speaker at the <a href="https://www.science2market.ch/">Innosuisse Start-up Training Business Concept</a> weekly course.</p> <p>He delved into the financing part of a start-up, how to attract investors, showing them we know the market’s pain and that possible clients have already shown interest in the product. Aside his great sharing of experience in this start-up ecosystem, he suggested the following book : <a href="https://trilliondollarcoach.com/">Trillion Dollar Coach</a> by <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/eric-schmidt-02158951/">Eric Schmidt</a>, <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/jonathanrosenberggoogle/">Jonathan Rosenberg</a>, and <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/alaneagle/">Alan Eagle</a> as being THE book to read. Keen on knowing what was giving him stars in the eyes when suggesting this book, I decided to give it a try.</p> <p>I grabbed the book for a few bucks on <a href="https://www.vinted.fr/catalog?search_text=trillion%20dollar%20coach">Vinted</a> and began reading it. What I can say first, is that I really enjoyed the accessibility and easiness of reading, plus it is a quick read !</p> <p>The book tells the story of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bill_Campbell_(business_executive)">Bill Campbell</a>, ‘coach’ of a lot of big names in the Silicon Valley. The authors make us walk through the path of being a manager (leader?) to building your team as an entity of support, respect, trust and love. Yes, love. Surprisingly, it seems to be one of the key points even in business to grow a successful company!</p> <p>I genuinely liked the structure of the book and the Take Home Messages at the end of each advice. Plus, they have done the effort to be research-based, adding even more value to their tips.</p> <p>Also, I am well aware that this book is written by white males, working in a highly competitive, tech environment. They also acknowledge this and address few points about that, which is a good point for them. In that sense, inclusion in a broader way is something I feel is missing in this book.</p> <p>If you want to read it, pin me and I can lend it to you with pleasure ! I look forward to talking about it with you if you have read it ! Please do not hesitate ☀️</p> <hr/> <p>Here are five tips that grasped my attention :</p> <ol> <li>Sharing what we enjoy outside work make the team care more about their teammates. (<a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jbusres.2015.02.015">Geimer et al., 2015</a>; <a href="https://doi.org/10.1177/0956797610362675">Mehl et al., 2010</a>)</li> <li>Never tell people what to do. Listen and ask them questions instead. This way, they can refine their priorities and reassess their use of time and effort. (<a href="https://doi.org/10.5465/amr.2014.0537">Van Quaquebeque &amp; Felps, 2018</a>)</li> <li>No consensus. This is why I like the <a href="https://www.liberatingstructures.com/1-1-2-4-all/">1-2-all</a> method when working in groups, and I can say it was enjoyable by student <a href="https://elearning.unige.ch/formation">taking R courses I taught at TakeOver</a>.</li> <li>Give a constructive feedback when the person is feeling safe, never during or right after a moment of frustration. Let the frustration go away, so that the better the feedback and the better the listening.</li> <li>Caring about people can be trained. Ask about people’s lives outside of work, understand their families, etc. Also try elevator chat : “How is it going? What are you working on?” (<a href="https://doi.org/10.1177/000276420326021">Kanov et al., 2004</a>)</li> </ol>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="book"/><category term="management"/><category term="misc"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Trillion Dollar Coach book review]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">What skills have I acquired between my Bachelor and my Masters degree?</title><link href="https://kennethrioja.github.io/blog/2023/university-between-bachelor-and-master/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What skills have I acquired between my Bachelor and my Masters degree?"/><published>2023-11-29T15:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-11-29T15:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://kennethrioja.github.io/blog/2023/university-between-bachelor-and-master</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://kennethrioja.github.io/blog/2023/university-between-bachelor-and-master/"><![CDATA[<h1 id="a-bit-of-context">A bit of context</h1> <p>I finished my Bachelor of Psychology in June 2019 and while writing this blog post I am soon to finish my Masters of Learning and Teaching Technologies, hopefully in summer 2024 🤞. “5 years !” you must say, hold on and see what I have done. <em>Spoiler alert</em> : I did not spend a year under the palm trees.</p> <h1 id="research">Research</h1> <p>I spent five years as a <a ref="https://www.unige.ch/fapse/brainlearning/">research assistant at the Brain And Learning Bavelier Lab</a> where I designed scientific experiments in cognitive psychology as well as extracting and analyzing data. I also had the opportunity to <a href="https://kennethrioja.github.io/projects/#publications">publish scientific articles in peer-reviewed journals</a> collaborating with international renowned researchers. With this first enriching professional experience, I knew I wanted to create online tools for making people’s life easier or analyze data in an easy way while keeping myself on the programming side. That is why I chose to pursue a <a href="https://maltt.unige.ch/">Master in Learning and Teaching Technologies</a> (<a href="https://edutechwiki.unige.ch/fmediawiki/index.php?title=Utilisateur:Kenneth_Rioja">link to my Masters Projects page</a>). This will lead to a Masters thesis focusing on learning analytics where I am currently analyzing data from a museum video game (an ‘epistemic’ video game to be more precise, aka. ‘serious’ video game but this term is inaccurate for <a href="https://kennethrioja.github.io/">several reasons</a>).<br/> <em>Rigor</em>, <em>critical thinking</em> and <em>determination</em> are the skills I can extract from these experiences.</p> <h1 id="ux--project-management">UX &amp; project management</h1> <p>The latter curriculum allowed me to engage in real-life projects collaborating with third-parties such as <a href="https://kennethrioja.github.io/projects/vg_findher">Bilingo</a> and the <a href="https://kennethrioja.github.io/projects/ux_unigefaclab">UNIGE FacLab</a>. I followed <a href="https://www.editions-eyrolles.com/Livre/9782212141436/methodes-de-design-ux">user-centered design</a> and <a href="https://dschool.stanford.edu/resources/getting-started-with-design-thinking">design thinking</a> approaches. Tools and methods used were: figma, semi-structured interviews (e.g., storytelling), customer analysis, user analysis (e.g., personas, experience maps), competitive analysis, card sorting (e.g., similarity matrices, dendrogram). I also developed my entrepreneurial mindset during the <a href="https://www.science2market.ch/">Business Concept Training run by EPFL Innovation Park</a> where I teamed up with two other colleagues on a house retrofit project. One of the main approach to the project development was to conduct more than 30 interviews to have a clear customer segmentation for instance.<br/> <em>Listening to users and customers</em> about their <em>problems</em> and analyzing their <em>needs</em> in order to <em>find solutions</em> or to <em>enhance an aspect of a product</em> is something I know I can help with in my future career.</p> <h1 id="project-based-learning--soft-skills">Project-based learning &amp; soft skills</h1> <p>I also experienced other aspects to projects during my Masters curriculum. First, as a student at the <a href="https://www.42lausanne.ch/">Computer Science School, 42 Lausanne</a>, I experienced an immersive project-based learning curriculum – no teachers, no courses, no schedule (<a href="https://kennethrioja.github.io/">how does it work ?</a>). Furthermore, I was hired as a <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/feed/update/urn:li:activity:7046450909467336704/">facilitator for a project-based course “Comprendre le Numérique”</a> at the University of Geneva during two consecutive years. The goal was to guide students on a concrete project allowing them to develop their soft skills such as teamwork, problem solving, communication, organization, critical thinking and communication. I was also given the opportunity to <a href="https://www.unige.ch/numerique/take-over">tutor on R and Prolific/Qualtrics</a>, these crash courses were given by students and for students.<br/> These experiences allowed me to be <em>adaptive</em>, to <em>learn fast</em> and to effectively <em>switch between tasks</em>.</p> <h1 id="software-development--data-analysis">Software development &amp; data analysis</h1> <p>Thanks to the 42 School, I am confident in using <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">C</code> and <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">C++</code> languages, in particular and among other projects, I wrote a sorting algorithm (insertion-sort), a shell and an IRC server. Setting up <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">virtual machines</code> and a <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Docker</code> <em>manually</em> were other projects at the school. In my spare time, I enjoy attending Game Jams with friends to create video games using <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Unity</code> and <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">C#</code> (<a href="https://kennethrioja.github.io/projects">link</a>). At the lab, I was told to create online tasks such as the <a href="https://kennethrioja.github.io/projects/misc_tova">TOVA</a> while using a <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">JavaScript</code> framework <a href="https://www.jspsych.org/7.3/">jspsych</a>. In another project at the lab, I needed to <a href="https://kennethrioja.github.io/projects/da_ranalyses">visualize and analyze data</a> using <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">R</code> and its statistical tools such as type-I ANOVA, correlations, t-tests (extreme group comparison). About visualization, I also dig into <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">visual network analysis</code> and <a href="https://kennethrioja.github.io/projects/da_vnaintro">wrote an extended explanation and a shorter blog post about it</a>. This was the starting point of my Masters thesis where I used the same technique to tackle <a href="https://kennethrioja.github.io/projects/da_mastersthesis">complexity understanding</a>.<br/> Acquiring hard skills is enriching, but using soft skills to <em>bring together teams of designers/researchers and web developers/software engineers</em> to advance on a project is more powerful (<a href="https://kennethrioja.github.io/">I have been involved in such a project at the lab</a>).</p> <h1 id="whats-coming-next">What’s coming next</h1> <p>I am now writing my Masters thesis and continuing my journey as a master student. More projects are coming: end of the common core at the 42 school in Lausanne, the start-up I am helping with, another semester to mentor a group of student for the course “Comprendre le Numérique” and continuing my job as a researcher.</p> <p>And I am still looking for an internship, so please <a href="https://kennethrioja.github.io/">contact me 🎉</a> !</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="university"/><category term="work"/><category term="misc"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[my academic life between 2019 and 2023]]></summary></entry></feed>