<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://kennethrioja.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://kennethrioja.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2023-12-05T16:06:43+00:00</updated><id>https://kennethrioja.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>Research, EdTech, Video Games, Data Analysis, UX </subtitle><entry><title type="html">How to be a better leader?</title><link href="https://kennethrioja.github.io/blog/2023/be-a-better-leader/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How to be a better leader?"/><published>2023-12-04T13:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-12-04T13:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://kennethrioja.github.io/blog/2023/be-a-better-leader</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://kennethrioja.github.io/blog/2023/be-a-better-leader/"><![CDATA[<div class="row"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> </div> <div class="col-sm-5 mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/blog_book_TDC-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/blog_book_TDC-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/blog_book_TDC-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/blog_book_TDC.jpeg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" title="book trillion dollar coach" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> First, read this book (or at least the following review). </div> <p>One month ago, <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/aviram/">Avi Ram</a> (an experienced International Business Program Director and Change Manager) was the speaker at the <a href="https://www.science2market.ch/">Innosuisse Start-up Training Business Concept</a> weekly course.</p> <p>He delved into the financing part of a start-up, how to attract investors, showing them we know the market’s pain and that possible clients have already shown interest in the product. Aside his great sharing of experience in this start-up ecosystem, he suggested the following book : <a href="https://trilliondollarcoach.com/">Trillion Dollar Coach</a> by <a href="https://twitter.com/ericschmidt">Eric Schmidt</a>, <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/jonathanrosenberggoogle/">Jonathan Rosenberg</a>, and <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/alaneagle/">Alan Eagle</a> as being THE book to read. Keen on knowing what was giving him stars in the eyes when suggesting this book, I decided to give it a try.</p> <p>I grabbed the book for a few bucks on <a href="https://www.vinted.fr/catalog?search_text=trillion%20dollar%20coach">Vinted</a> and began reading it. What I can say first, is that I really enjoyed the accessibility and easiness of reading, plus it is a quick read !</p> <p>The book tells the story of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bill_Campbell_(business_executive)">Bill Campbell</a>, ‘coach’ of a lot of big names in the Silicon Valley. The authors make us walk through the path of being a manager (leader?) to building your team as an entity of support, respect, trust and love. Yes, love. Surprisingly, it seems to be one of the key points even in business to grow a successful company!</p> <p>I genuinely liked the structure of the book and the Take Home Messages at the end of each advice. Plus, they have done the effort to be research-based, adding even more value to their tips.</p> <p>Also, I am well aware that this book is written by white males, working in a highly competitive, tech environment. They also acknowledge this and address few points about that, which is a good point for them. In that sense, inclusion in a broader way is something I feel is missing in this book.</p> <p>If you want to read it, pin me and I can lend it to you with pleasure ! I look forward to talking about it with you if you have read it ! Please do not hesitate ☀️</p> <hr/> <p>Here are five tips that grasped my attention :</p> <ol> <li>Sharing what we enjoy outside work make the team care more about their teammates. (<a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jbusres.2015.02.015">Geimer et al., 2015</a>; <a href="https://doi.org/10.1177/0956797610362675">Mehl et al., 2010</a>)</li> <li>Never tell people what to do. Listen and ask them questions instead. This way, they can refine their priorities and reassess their use of time and effort. (<a href="https://doi.org/10.5465/amr.2014.0537">Van Quaquebeque &amp; Felps, 2018</a>)</li> <li>No consensus. This is why I like the <a href="https://www.liberatingstructures.com/1-1-2-4-all/">1-2-all</a> method when working in groups, and I can say it was enjoyable by student <a href="https://elearning.unige.ch/formation">taking R courses I taught at TakeOver</a>.</li> <li>Give a constructive feedback when the person is feeling safe, never during or right after a moment of frustration. Let the frustration go away, so that the better the feedback and the better the listening.</li> <li>Caring about people can be trained. Ask about people’s lives outside of work, understand their families, etc. Also try elevator chat : “How is it going? What are you working on?” (<a href="https://doi.org/10.1177/000276420326021">Kanov et al., 2004</a>)</li> </ol>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="book"/><category term="management"/><category term="startup"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Trillion Dollar Coach book review]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">What skills have I acquired between my Bachelor and my Masters degree?</title><link href="https://kennethrioja.github.io/blog/2023/university-between-bachelor-and-master/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What skills have I acquired between my Bachelor and my Masters degree?"/><published>2023-11-29T15:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-11-29T15:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://kennethrioja.github.io/blog/2023/university-between-bachelor-and-master</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://kennethrioja.github.io/blog/2023/university-between-bachelor-and-master/"><![CDATA[<h1 id="a-bit-of-context">A bit of context</h1> <p>I finished my Bachelor of Psychology in June 2019 and while writing this blog post I am soon to finish my Masters of Learning and Teaching Technologies, hopefully in summer 2024 🤞. “5 years !” you must say, hold on and see what I have done. <em>Spoiler alert</em> : I did not spend a year under the palm trees.</p> <h1 id="research">Research</h1> <p>I spent five years as a <a ref="https://www.unige.ch/fapse/brainlearning/">research assistant at the Brain And Learning Bavelier Lab</a> where I designed scientific experiments in cognitive psychology as well as extracting and analyzing data. I also had the opportunity to <a href="https://kennethrioja.github.io/projects/#publications">publish scientific articles in peer-reviewed journals</a> collaborating with international renowned researchers. With this first enriching professional experience, I knew I wanted to create online tools for making people’s life easier or analyze data in an easy way while keeping myself on the programming side. That is why I chose to pursue a <a href="https://maltt.unige.ch/">Master in Learning and Teaching Technologies</a> (<a href="https://edutechwiki.unige.ch/fmediawiki/index.php?title=Utilisateur:Kenneth_Rioja">link to my Masters Projects page</a>). This will lead to a Masters thesis focusing on learning analytics where I am currently analyzing data from a museum video game (an ‘epistemic’ video game to be more precise, aka. ‘serious’ video game but this term is inaccurate for <a href="https://kennethrioja.github.io/">several reasons</a>).<br/> <em>Rigor</em>, <em>critical thinking</em> and <em>determination</em> are the skills I can extract from these experiences.</p> <h1 id="ux--project-management">UX &amp; project management</h1> <p>The latter curriculum allowed me to engage in real-life projects collaborating with third-parties such as <a href="https://kennethrioja.github.io/projects/vg_findher">Bilingo</a> and the <a href="https://kennethrioja.github.io/projects/ux_unigefaclab">UNIGE FacLab</a>. I followed <a href="https://www.editions-eyrolles.com/Livre/9782212141436/methodes-de-design-ux">user-centered design</a> and <a href="https://dschool.stanford.edu/resources/getting-started-with-design-thinking">design thinking</a> approaches. Tools and methods used were: figma, semi-structured interviews (e.g., storytelling), customer analysis, user analysis (e.g., personas, experience maps), competitive analysis, card sorting (e.g., similarity matrices, dendrogram). I also developed my entrepreneurial mindset during the <a href="https://www.science2market.ch/">Business Concept Training run by EPFL Innovation Park</a> where I teamed up with two other colleagues on a house retrofit project. One of the main approach to the project development was to conduct more than 30 interviews to have a clear customer segmentation for instance.<br/> <em>Listening to users and customers</em> about their <em>problems</em> and analyzing their <em>needs</em> in order to <em>find solutions</em> or to <em>enhance an aspect of a product</em> is something I know I can help with in my future career.</p> <h1 id="project-based-learning--soft-skills">Project-based learning &amp; soft skills</h1> <p>I also experienced other aspects to projects during my Masters curriculum. First, as a student at the <a href="https://www.42lausanne.ch/">Computer Science School, 42 Lausanne</a>, I experienced an immersive project-based learning curriculum – no teachers, no courses, no schedule (<a href="https://kennethrioja.github.io/">how does it work ?</a>). Furthermore, I was hired as a <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/feed/update/urn:li:activity:7046450909467336704/">facilitator for a project-based course “Comprendre le Numérique”</a> at the University of Geneva during two consecutive years. The goal was to guide students on a concrete project allowing them to develop their soft skills such as teamwork, problem solving, communication, organization, critical thinking and communication. I was also given the opportunity to <a href="https://www.unige.ch/numerique/take-over">tutor on R and Prolific/Qualtrics</a>, these crash courses were given by students and for students.<br/> These experiences allowed me to be <em>adaptive</em>, to <em>learn fast</em> and to effectively <em>switch between tasks</em>.</p> <h1 id="software-development--data-analysis">Software development &amp; data analysis</h1> <p>Thanks to the 42 School, I am confident in using <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">C</code> and <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">C++</code> languages, in particular and among other projects, I wrote a sorting algorithm (insertion-sort), a shell and an IRC server. Setting up <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">virtual machines</code> and a <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Docker</code> <em>manually</em> were other projects at the school. In my spare time, I enjoy attending Game Jams with friends to create video games using <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Unity</code> and <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">C#</code> (<a href="https://kennethrioja.github.io/projects">link</a>). At the lab, I was told to create online tasks such as the <a href="https://kennethrioja.github.io/projects/misc_tova">TOVA</a> while using a <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">JavaScript</code> framework <a href="https://www.jspsych.org/7.3/">jspsych</a>. In another project at the lab, I needed to <a href="https://kennethrioja.github.io/projects/da_ranalyses">visualize and analyze data</a> using <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">R</code> and its statistical tools such as type-I ANOVA, correlations, t-tests (extreme group comparison). About visualization, I also dig into <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">visual network analysis</code> and <a href="https://kennethrioja.github.io/projects/da_vnaintro">wrote an extended explanation and a shorter blog post about it</a>. This was the starting point of my Masters thesis where I used the same technique to tackle <a href="https://kennethrioja.github.io/projects/da_mastersthesis">complexity understanding</a>.<br/> Acquiring hard skills is enriching, but using soft skills to <em>bring together teams of designers/researchers and web developers/software engineers</em> to advance on a project is more powerful (<a href="https://kennethrioja.github.io/">I have been involved in such a project at the lab</a>).</p> <h1 id="whats-coming-next">What’s coming next</h1> <p>I am now writing my Masters thesis and continuing my journey as a master student. More projects are coming: end of the common core at the 42 school in Lausanne, the start-up I am helping with, another semester to mentor a group of student for the course “Comprendre le Numérique” and continuing my job as a researcher.</p> <p>And I am still looking for an internship, so please <a href="https://kennethrioja.github.io/">contact me 🎉</a> !</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="university"/><category term="work"/><category term="misc"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[my academic life between 2019 and 2023]]></summary></entry></feed>